Take care of everybody בבא בתרא *Bava Batra* י"א *Yud Alef* is
today's דף *Daf* and we pick up on י' עמוד ב' *Yud
Amud Bet* but we're God willing catching up today and we pick
up here where it says we're wrapping up the סוגיא sugya *Sugya*
of צדקה tzedakah. *Tzedakah* and תניא tanya *Tanya* we are in the
middle-sized lines middle-width lines 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 about
eight lines down okay in י' עמוד ב' *Yud Amud Bet* תניא
אמר להם amar lahem רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan בן זכאי לתלמידיו *Tanya
amar lahem Rabbi Yochanan ben Zakkai letalmidav* רבי יוחנן בן זכאי *Rabbi
Yochanan ben Zakkai* said to his students בני מהו שאמר הכתוב *Banai
mahu she'amar hakatuv* what is meant by the verse צדקה תרומם גוי
וחסד לאומים tzedakah teromem goy ve-chesed le'umim. חטאת chatat, *Tzedakah teromem goy
vechesed leumim chatat*? The righteousness or צדקה tzedakah *Tzedakah* in this context
will lift up a nation and חסד chesed *Chesed* you know acts
of kindness לאומים *leumim* for nations חטאת *chatat* is a sin. What
does that mean it's a sin? What does that mean? Okay so
that's really a hard פסוק pasuk *Pasuk* to parse so let's see
what the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* does with it. I actually looked at
one translation actually interpreted חסד chesed *Chesed* not as acts of kindness
but as
iniquity right like חסד chesed. הוא *Chesed hu* like by the פסוק
pasuk. *Pasuk* about כי תקח אחותו חסד chesed היא *Ki tikach achoto
chesed hi* or something like that.
One דרשה *Drasha* means a קללה *Klala*.
Anyway it's a difficult פסוק pasuk *Pasuk* so let's see what he
does with it. What do you do with this פסוק pasuk. *Pasuk*?
נענה רבי אליעזר ואמר *Na'anah Rabbi Eliezer ve'amar* צדקה תרומם גוי tzedakah
teromem goy *Tzedakah teromem goy*. צדקה tzedakah *Tzedakah* will lift up a
גוי goy *Goy*. What's a גוי goy *Goy*? אלו ישראל elu Yisrael
*Eilu Yisrael*. גוי *Goy* of course is ישראל Yisrael. *Yisrael* דכתיב ומי
כעמך ישראל גוי אחד בארץ d'chtiv u'mi k'amcha Yisrael goy echad ba'aretz,
*dechtiv umi ke'amcha Yisrael goy echad ba'aretz*. Okay וחסד לאומים חטאת v'chesed
le'umim chatat, *vechesed leumim chatat*. Who's a לאום *Le'om*? כל צדקה tzedakah,
וחסד שאומות she'umot עובדי כוכבים ovdei kochavim. עושים *Kol tzedakah vechesed she'umot
ovdei
kochavim osim*. לאום *Le'om* and אומות umot? *Umot* right? That any צדקה
tzedakah *Tzedakah* and חסד chesed, *Chesed* that the nations or the אומות
umot עובדי כוכבים *umot ovdei kochavim* do חטא להן *cheit lahen*. We
get credit for all of our צדקה tzedakah, *Tzedakah* and for them
when they give צדקה tzedakah *Tzedakah* it's a sin. How could you
say it's a sin? שאינם עושים אלא להתגדל בו l'hitgadel bo *she'einam
osim ela lehitgadel bo*. They don't really do it לשם שמים *leshaim
shamayim*. They only do it for their own purposes. They only do
it so they can look like these great philanthropists and so what
can I tell you? שנאמר she'ne'emar *shene'emar*. Okay now by the way
of course this is רבי יוחנן בן זכאי *Rabbi Yochanan ben Zakkai*
right? So we are talking right at the sort of you know
at the time of the חורבן בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash *churban Beit
Hamikdash*. I don't know if right before or right after but obviously
we don't have too good of an attitude towards Rome. Alright and
of course people remember that famous גמרא Gemara *Gemara* which of course
was the basis for the famous Monty Python scene in the beginning
of עבודה זרה *Avodah Zarah* which is like they're all sitting around
the table and they're saying
like you know all the good the Romans did they think they
did so much good to us they built the streets and the
water and the this and the that and they were only doing
it for their own interests you know and then there was a
little debate there actually because there was a תנא Tanna, *Tanna* that
actually said no actually we should be grateful for that exactly. So
anyway so here you have them living in the Roman Empire clearly
benefiting from everything Rome has done to create peace and to create
infrastructure and water and all of that but having Rome as the
oppressor and
being about to destroy the בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash, *Beit Hamikdash*. So
how do you look at that right? So here we're sort of
translating all of that kindness as they're only doing it for their
own glory and it's ultimately a sin you know you can't attribute
anything good to them. Okay שנאמר she-ne-emar *shene'emar*. די להוון מהקרבין ניחוחין
לאלה שמיא ומצליין לחיי מלכא ובנוהי *di lehevon makrivin nichochin l'eloah shamaya
umetzalyin l'chayei malka u'venohi*. And here we get it from another
non-Jewish kingdom that ruled over which was in the time of עזרא
*Ezra* right when they were building the בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash *Beit
Hamikdash*. So there actually they were contributing to the building of the
בית המקדש *Beit Hamikdash* and it says די להוון מהקרבין ניחוחין לאלה
שמיא *di lehevon makrivin nichochin l'eloah shamaya* that here is this support
and money that you should bring sacrifices to the God of heaven
ומצליין לחיי מלכא ובנוהי *umetzalyin l'chayei malka u'venohi* and pray for the
life of the king and his son. So I'm not just סתם
*stam* לשם שמים *leshaim shamayim* ultimately it should be to pray for
us. ודעבד הכי *ude'avid hachi*. Now the גמרא Gemara, *Gemara* says one
minute somebody who acts this way לאו צדקה tzedakah, גמורה היא *lav
tzedakah gemurah hi* is this not real צדקה tzedakah *Tzedakah*? והתניא v'hatanya,
*vehatanya* האומר סלע זו לצדקה בשביל שיחיה בני ובשביל שאזכה לחיי העולם
הבא *ha'omer sela zu litzdakah bishvil sheyichye beni uvishvil she'ezkeh lechayei ha'olam
haba*. Somebody gives צדקה tzedakah *Tzedakah* and has in mind like my
son is sick I want him to get better I want to
get עולם הבא *olam haba*. He has non-לשם שמים *leshaim shamayim* intentions
in mind הרי זה צדיק tzadik גמור *harei zeh tzaddik gamur*. He
is still a צדיק tzadik גמור *tzaddik gamur*. Now that's a little
bit of a big statement a צדיק גמור *tzaddik gamur* when you
say that? So רש"י Rashi, *Rashi* responds and רש"י Rashi *Rashi* says
הרי זה צדיק גמור *harei zeh tzaddik gamur* רש"י Rashi *Rashi* says
על דבר זה מחשבה זו *al davar zeh machshava zo*. Okay this
act still you know we don't see any less of you because
of this act whether you're a צדיק גמור *tzaddik gamur* in general
might depend on how you act in the rest of your
life. I had a רבי *Rebbe* who once said to me that
he thought that maybe originally it was a you know it said
like it was like with a צ'יפ צ'יפ *chip-chip* הרי זה צדיק
גמור *harei zeh tzaddik gamur* whatever or צדקה tzedakah גמורה *tzedakah gemurah*
which is the phrase the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* used right before צדקה
tzedakah גמורה *tzedakah gemurah* which would make a little better sense but
I looked at all the parallel manuscripts and they all have צדיק
גמור *tzaddik gamur* so I don't know it's a good theory. Anyway
so הרי זה צדיק גמור *harei zeh tzaddik gamur* לא Lo, קשיא
כאן בישראל כאן בעובדי כוכבים kan b'Yisrael kan b'ovdei kochavim, *lo kashya
kan b'Yisrael kan b'ovdei kochavim*. Fine for Jews you can give it
שלא לשמה shelo lishma, *shelo lishma* but for non-Jews it's a sin
or certainly no credit. Now what does that I mean why should
there be a difference? So if you look at רש"י, Rashi כאן
בישראל כאן בעובדי כוכבים, ישראל דעתו לשמים, Yisrael da'ato lishmayim, בין יחיה
בין לא יחיה, ben yihye ben lo yihye, אינו מהרהר אחר מידת
הדין. eino meharher achar midat hadin. You want it to be, you
know, you're hoping that God will be respond response to your prayers
in that case, or you know, or do what you're looking for,
but even if not, you say you know ultimately I trust in
God and you accept God's judgment and you don't regret having given
the צדקה. tzedakah אבל עכו"ם אינו נותן אלא למנת שיחיה aval akum
eino noten ela limnat sheyichye ואם לאו מתחרט. v'im lav mitcharet. And
if not, he regrets having done it. So it's a שלא לשמה,
shelo lishma you know we always have שלא לשמה shelo lishma intentions,
I don't know we always, but whatever, I'll speak for myself. Okay,
anyway. It's very high to pure לשמה, lishma, but that doesn't mean
because there's שלא לשמה shelo lishma elements that there's not also לשמה
lishma elements. Okay, and that but here it's going to it's assumed
to be all שלא לשמה shelo lishma. and if it wasn't achieved
they didn't want to do it at all. All right, so that's
one approach. Okay, נענה רבי יהושע na'ana Rabbi Yehoshua that was obviously
an interjection, right? That was all Aramaic. We're back to the ברייתא
braita back to the Hebrew. נענה רבי יהושע ואמר na'ana Rabbi Yehoshua
v'amar צדקה תרומם גוי Tzedakah teromem goy sorry אלו
ישראל Yisrael דכתיב ומי כעמך ישראל d'chtiv u'mi k'amcha Yisrael גוי
אחד goy echad. בארץ, same thing. וחסד לאומים חטאת, v'chesed le'umim chatat
כל צדקה וחסד שעובדי
כוכבים עושים kol tzedakah v'chesed she'ovdei kochavim osim
or sorry whatever, what's the original גרסא? girsa? Anybody have the נכרים
nochrim or אומות? umot Whatever, probably not עובדי כוכבים. Anyway, שאומות probably
אומות העולם umot ha'olam I'm guessing, שאומות העולם עושים she'umot ha'olam osim
חטא הוא להם. cheit hu lahem. Why? שאין עושים אלא כדי שתמשך
מלכותן. she'ein osim ela k'dei shetimshach malchutan.
Doesn't seem like there's a big difference here between whether you're doing
it for your own honor or to extend your I mean, you
know, to have a long rule. I mean, there is some difference.
שנאמר she-ne-emar and that there the פסוק is להן מלכא מלכי ישפר
עלך lehen malka milchi yishpar alach by Daniel וחטיך בצדקה פרוק. v'chata'ach
b'tzedakah perok. Therefore, you know, Daniel says to the king, you know,
you you should you should atone for your sin with צדקה tzedakah
ועויתך במיחן ענין v'avayach b'michan anayin and your iniquity with being kind
to the poor. הן להוי ארכא לשלוותך. hen lehavay archa l'shalvatach. That
way there will be a length to your kingdom. So, another type
of a שלא לשמה. Right. Well maybe that's a good way in
practical terms that's a good way of thinking it. Okay. Which is
funny because the previous one said מצלין לחיי מלכא ובנוהי metzalin l'chayei
malka u'vnohei which also seemed to be an extending the like reign
of the kingdom and not necessarily the glory of the kingdom. So
the supporting פסוקים psukim seem to be saying the seem to be
saying the same thing although the statements are different. One is about
glory and the other is about success. David what were you going
to say?
I was just going to say that the you know just on
the statements without the פסוקים, psukim, the second one seems to say
that it's seems to apply only to the rulers, meaning if an
average עכו"ם akum would not...
Oh, because it's מלכותן malchutan and therefore it's very limited to that
פסוק. That's a good point. And the other one was להתגדל בו
could apply to anybody. Right. And that's an interesting question, are we
talking about the like because I put it in the framework because
of these פסוקים psukim of you know the government doing all of
this amazing thing for its inhabitants you know for its citizens we
would say, right? But are we also talking about an individual non-Jew
and the צדקה tzedakah that he gives or we talking about sort
of like a sort of a communal or a national one? I
mean, you know there's a very beautiful רב משה Rav Moshe where
he
was asked a question about is it permissible to like I I
think something I forget what it was, I think it was like
either misrepresent yourself you know in terms of getting some grant from
the government or maybe it was about
ישיבה בחורים yeshiva bachurim cheating on their regents or whatever like so
first of all he like didn't want he he said חס ושלום
chas v'shalom nobody really ever did this you know whatever he like
you know didn't want to deny the possibility that it was really
happening. But anyway, in theory he said you know he said his
תשובה tshuva basically said, listen guys, this isn't Soviet this is not
this is not let me try again, this isn't Tsarist Russia or
Soviet anyway, this isn't Tsarist Russia, this government he said is בעלת
חסד ba'alat chesed and its whole intent is to do חסד עם
יושביה chesed im yoshveha and you know and we should be yeah
he talking about the United States you know and and therefore our
attitude to it has to be very different than the attitude that
Jews have had to the sort of you know their host government
for you know millennia. Right so I'll send it out. Okay, that
רב משה. Rav Moshe. Anyway, so so the point yes, so anyway,
so okay, so the point is are we thinking in terms of
that about how do we look at the good that the you
know governments do or are we think about in terms of individuals?
That's a very good point.
I'm managing the listserv if I can get at it.
Oh yeah that's Dov Weinstein I'll put you in touch. Okay anyway
okay moving on. Okay נענה רבן גמליאל ואמר na'ana Rabban Gamliel v'amar
צדקה תרומם גוי אלו ישראל tzedakah teromem goy elu Yisrael דכתיב ומי
כעמך ישראל וחסד לאומים חטאת ve-chesed le'umim chatat. כל צדקה וחסד שעכו"ם
עושים kol tzedakah v'chesed she'akum osim אין חטא הוא להם ein cheit
hu lahem שאין עושים אלא להתיהר בו. she'ein osim ela l'hityaher bo.
I do wonder and I have to go check the גרסאות girsot
but going back to exactly this question the shift from אומות probably
was אומות העולם עושים umot ha'olam osim as opposed to שעכו"ם עושים.
she'akum osim. אומות means at the national level, right? And now we've
shifted to עכו"ם akum which means at the individual level. Okay so
it does seem like maybe exactly this difference. I hadn't picked up
on that. להתייהר בהן. Lehityayer bahen. Where were we? It's only done
to look make yourself look righteous. Making yourself look righteous is different
than glory. No, glory is, you know, righteous is פרום. frum. Everybody
thinks I'm so פרום, frum, I'm so religious, okay? אלא להתייהר בהן.
Ela lehityayer bahen. Where was I? I skipped my line.
וכל המתייהר נופל בגיהנום. Vechol hamityayer nofel be-Gehinnom. And by the way,
anybody who makes themselves look overly righteous than they are, you know,
as it is said, זד יהיר לץ שמו. Zed yahir letz shemo.
This is
a, whatever, a transgressive person, acts פרום, frum, acts religious, then he
is really a לץ, letz, he's a mocker, עושה בעברת זדון. oseh
be-evrat zadon. He does with anger his sin. אין עברה אלא גיהנום
שנאמר יום עברה היום ההוא. Ein evrah ela Gehinnom shene'emar yom evrah
hayom hahu. Okay. אמר רבן גמליאל, Amar Rabban Gamliel, עדיין אנו
צריכים למודעי.
adayin
anu tzerichim le-Modai.
Ah, we still need the המודעי, HaModai, Rabbi Eleazar HaModai.
אמר רבי אלעזר המודעי אומר, Amar Rabbi Eleazar HaModai omer, צדקה תרומם
גוי אלו ישראל, Tzedakah teromem goy elu Yisrael, דכתיב מי כעמך ישראל
גוי אחד בארץ, dechtiv mi ke-amcha Yisrael goy echad ba'aretz, גוי אחד.
echad, וחסד לאומים חטאת כל צדקה וחסד שאומות העולם עושים חטא הוא
להם. Ve-chesed le'umim chatat kol tzedakah ve-chesed she-umot ha-olam osim cheit hu
lahem.
They do it as a way of cursing us, meaning showing, you
know, themselves better than we are, and not just as a way
of making themselves look פרום, frum, but making, you know, us look
bad. שנאמר ויבא וישם כאשר דבר כי חטאתם להשם ולא שמעתם בקולו
ויקרה לכם הדבר הזה. Shene'emar vayavo vayasham ka'asher dibber ki chatatem la-Hashem
velo shematem be-kolo vayikrah lachem ha-davar ha-zeh. Like
this is where at the time when the בית המקדש was being
destroyed and נבוזראדן Nevuzaradan was saying that ירמיהו, Yirmiyahu, you know, you
get this because you were not, because you haven't fulfilled God's מצוות.
mitzvos. So if they're doing צדקה, tzedakah it must be to show
themselves as פרום-ער frummer than us and to make us look bad.
Okay. נענה רב נחוניא בן הקנה ואמר Na'anah Rav Nechunya ben HaKanah
ve-amar צדקה tzedakah תרומם גוי וחסד לאומים.
Okay now, here is... so until now it's been pretty bad about
the attitude towards either non-Jewish nations or individual non-Jews around this. Now
we're going to make it even worse. נענה רב נחוניא בן הקנה
ואומר Na'anah Rav Nechunya ben HaKanah ve-omer צדקה תרומם גוי וחסד לישראל.
tzedakah teromem goy ve-chesed le-Yisrael. Okay,
so צדקה tzedakah will lift up the nation as will חסד lift
up the גוי and גוי means ישראל. ולאומים חטאת. Ule'umim chatat.
And non-Jews only have sin. Okay. So he puts the comma at
a different place. אמר להם רבן יוחנן בן זכאי, Amar lahem Rabban
Yochanan ben Zakkai, דורס את כל הפסוק הזה. dores et kol ha-pasuk
ha-zeh. Okay. נראין דברי רב נחוניא בן הקנה מדברי ומדבריכם. Nirin divrei
Rav Nechunya ben HaKanah mi-divrai u-mi-divreichem. Ah, this seems to be the
best פשט. pshat. לפי שהוא נותן צדקה וחסד לישראל. Lefi she-hu noten
tzedakah ve-chesed le-Yisrael.
He managed to get the חסד word in the פסוק to apply
to ישראל as well. Not only do we צדקה, tzedakah we even
do חסד. Okay. ולאקום חטאת. U-le-Akum chatat.
And עכו"ם Akum just has sin. We don't even sort of acknowledge
the חסד that they do, right? Which is a difference. Like, one
thing is to acknowledge the חסד, but say oh it's שלא לשם
שמים, shelo lishmah shamayim, they're doing it to make us look bad,
they're doing it for themselves. The other is to not even acknowledge
it. So that's the best, I guess, I don't know. דהוא. De-hu.
Okay. Now the גמרא Gemara, says מכלל דהוא נמי אמר. Michlal de-hu
nami amar. So he says better than my approach, he didn't tell
us his approach. מכלל דהוא נמי אמר. Michlal de-hu nami amar. So
it sounds like he also had a read of this פסוק. What
was it? דתניא אמר להם רבן יוחנן בן זכאי כשם שהחטאת מכפרת
על ישראל כך צדקה מכפרת על אומות העולם. Detanya amar lahem Rabban
Yochanan ben Zakkai keshem she-ha-chatat mechaperet al Yisrael kach tzedakah mechaperet al
umot ha-olam. So he actually reads it in a positive way. He's
the one person who reads it in a positive way, right? צדקה
tzedakah תרומם גוי like we've been saying וחסד לאומים חטאת. Yes, it
serves as a קרבן חטאת. korban chatat. So that idea we had
alluded to before, צדקה tzedakah is a type of a קרבן. korban.
Here we're saying it in terms of the non-Jews. When they do
a צדקה, tzedakah. that atones for them. Okay, so that's actually... so
if he thought, if he had this positive attitude, why did he
embrace, you know, the last approach which seemed to have been the
most negative one? I really don't understand that. He himself had a
more positive read and he embraced the last approach which was the
most negative. It also raises interesting questions about maybe, maybe, it also
raises you know Rabban Yochanan ben Zakkai who negotiated with the Romans
you know in terms of יבנה, Yavneh, you know, so not wanting
to have such a negative approach. Okay.
Now another story.
Yeah, earlier שיטה shittah or whatever.
Yeah, that's what Michael just said. Maybe it changed over time. Okay.
איפרא הורמיז אימיה דשבור מלכא. Ifra Hormiz imei de-Shavor Malka. We had
her before. Remember she sent money and she said use it for
a big מצוה mitzvah and we discussed פדיון שבויים. pidyon shvuyim. So
איפרא הורמיז Ifra Hormiz the mother of שבור מלכא Shavor Malka שדרה
ארבע מאה דינרי לקמיה דרבי אמי. shaddrah arba me'ah dinarei lekamei de-Rabbi
Ami. Sent four hundred דינרי dinarei to Rabbi Ami. Now this is
immediately in the context of a saying that צדקה that non-Jews give
is all for their own purposes and it's all a sin and
so on. So what do you do if they're giving you צדקה
not just you know they're directly giving צדקה to you. They're not
just building roads and you can be you know sort of be
you know say ah it's only for their own sake. They're giving
you money. Do you turn it down? Okay.
So she sent him four hundred דינרי, dinarei, let's take a look.
לקמיה דרבי אמי ולא קיבלינהו. Lekamei de-Rabbi Ami velo kibeilin-hu. And he
refused to accept them, presumably based on the earlier discussion. שדרינהו לקמיה
דרבא וקיבלינהו. Shadrin-hu lekamei de-Rava ve-kibeilin-hu. So fine, so they sent it
to Rava. Here Rava, here's four hundred דינרי, dinarei, distribute it to
the poor. וקיבלינהו Ve-kibeilin-hu and Rava was happy to accept it. Okay.
משום שלום מלכות. Mishum shalom malchus. Oh you know we want to
get along with the... Okay so she sent him four hundred דינרי.
dinari. Let's take a look. וקמיה דבי אמי ולא קיבלינהו v'kamei d'vei
Ami v'lo kiblinhu and he refused to accept them, presumably based on
the earlier discussion. שדרינהו קמיה דרבא, shadrinhu kamei d'Rava, so fine, so
they sent it to Rava. Here Rava, here's four hundred דינרי, dinari,
distribute it to the poor. וקיבלינהו v'kiblinhu and Rava was happy to
accept it. Okay. משום שלום מלכות. mishum shalom malchut. Oh you know
we want to get along with the government. Maybe, whatever, it's a
חטאת, whatever, they have their own purposes. Now it's interesting, you know,
what about the fact that I don't care if they have their
own purposes? You know we have עניים aniyim that we have to
support, doesn't that shouldn't that outweigh the other considerations? You might remember
this echoes an earlier discussion about Herod, right? Where the one who
gave advice to Herod to build a בית המקדש, the גמרא Gemara.
said well how was he complicit in the acts of this terrible
person? So it's a really interesting question. Yeah, but we need a
בית המקדש to get built, you know? So here it's interesting that
it's being framed as שלום מלכות shalom malchut and not direct care
of the עניים aniyim and that's going to continue. So let's take
a look. רבי אמי אקפיד. Rabbi Ami ikpid. רבי אמי Rabbi Ami
got upset. He says, I turned it down and you accepted it?
דשמע רבי אמי. dishma Rabbi Ami. רבי אמי, Rabbi Ami heard, אקפיד
ikpid and he got upset. אמר ליתא דלא רמי האי ביבש קצירה
תשברנה נשים באות מאירות אותה, amar leisa d’lo rami ha’i b'yavesh k'tzirah
tishavarna nashim ba'ot m'irot ota, when it's, you know, when it's saplings
or whatever dry out, then they'll be broken, when they lose their
זכות, zechut, then the non-Jewish nations will be broken, women will come
and מאירות אותה, m'irot ota, so רבנו גרשום Rabbeinu Gershom says, right,
it's to eat or or have rulership over them, have mastery over
them. Okay, so anyway, you know, why do you want to support
them by giving them
זכות? zechut? ורבא משום שלום מלכות v'Rava mishum shalom malchut and ורבא,
Rava, nah, you know, שלום מלכות shalom malchut is an overriding value.
By the way, it's also interesting because these are the אמוראים Amoraim
who had it much better under Persia than the Jews ever had
it under Rome, you know? And here they're still having this expressing
this approach. רבי אמי נמי משום שלום מלכות, Rabbi Ami nami mishum
shalom malchut, so didn't רבי אמי Rabbi Ami hear about שלום מלכות?
shalom malchut? No, דאיבעי ליה למיפלגיה לעניי עובדי כוכבים, de'iba lei lemipligei
l'aniyei ovdei kochavim, fine, accept the money, but don't give them merit,
don't help them, you know, so give it to non-Jewish poor, don't
give it to the Jewish poor. Which is interesting, they get more
merit if they give their צדקה to the Jewish poor than if
they give their צדקה to the non-Jewish poor. So don't help them
in that way. Or maybe it gets back to the earlier גמרא,
Gemara, like don't, it gives them a sense of like, you know,
like, you know, a superiority over the Jews. I am supporting the
Jewish poor. They're not supporting their own or they need me to
help support them. So maybe there's an element of don't allow them
that.
At the expense of your Jewish poor.
I understand, it is at the expense of the poor who need
it. ורבא נמי לעניי עובדי כוכבים יהבינהו v'Rava nami l'aniyei ovdei kochavim
yavinhu and ורבא נמי לעניי עובדי כוכבים יהבינהו. v'Rava nami l'aniyei ovdei
kochavim yavinhu. Yeah, Rava figured that out. Rava also gave it to
the poor, to the poor of the non-Jews. So don't worry.
ורבי אמי דאקפיד, v'Rabbi Ami d'ikpid, so then why did רבי אמי
Rabbi Ami get upset? We're we're like minimizing any possible difference between
them. הוא דלא סיימו קמיה hu d'lo siyemu kamei because when they
told him that Rava took the money, they didn't end the story
and say and he gave it to the non-Jewish poor. Okay, so
it's very interesting, right? This idea that you have poor who obviously
could benefit from the money and in order to not allow the
עכו"ם Akum to give them their זכות zechut or the sense of
superiority or whatever, we're actually going to not give it to our
own poor. Okay, so if you take a look at רש"י, Rashi.
now רש"י Rashi is very interesting. Now רש"י Rashi, says, רש"י Rashi
is bothered by a question. Isn't it גניבת דעת, gneivat da'at, says
רש"י. Rashi They gave you the money and they assumed that you
were going to give it to the Jewish poor. They know how
to give it to the non-Jewish poor. So, and you're giving it
to the non-Jewish poor, what about גניבת דעת? gneivat da'at? So a
good question, right? You're sort of not being honest with them. So
רש"י Rashi says, if you look at רש"י, Rashi, if two lines
down from the top, in the middle of the line, רש"י Rashi
says, דאסור לגנוב דעת הבריות ואפילו דעתו של עובד כוכבים אבל במנה
דמתפלגא לעניים אין גניבת דעת דאינהו נמי ידעי דישראל רגילין לפרנס עניי
עובד כוכבים כדאמרינן במסכת גיטין מפרנסין עניי עובד כוכבים עם עניי ישראל
מפני דרכי שלום. d'asur lignov da'at habriyot va'afilu da'ato shel oved kochavim
aval bimana d'mitpalga l'aniyim ein gneivat da'at d'innun nami yad'ei d'Yisrael regilin
l'farnes aniyei akum k'damrin masechet Gittin m'farnasin aniyei akum im aniyei Yisrael
mipnei darchei shalom.
So since they know that we sometimes also support non-Jewish poor, we're
not misrepresenting. They're giving it to us in our discretion. So since
some of our צדקה funds go to non-Jews, we'll we'll earmark this
for our non-Jewish poor.
But if she said specifically for Jewish poor.
Yeah, then רש"י Rashi would say then either you have to turn
it down or you have to give it to Jewish poor, and
that's the שלום מלכות shalom malchut issue. But again, I do find
it troubling that שלום מלכות shalom malchut is the only thing that
justifies that and not the real need to support your own poor.
Maybe this goes back to the earlier point, you know? That remember
the, you know, the גמרא Gemara earlier said you better support your
own poor because if not the government will come in and tax
you and then they'll take it over for you. So maybe the
point is we don't want to be dependent on the non-Jewish government
to support. We want, you know, like, you know, like the people
who say oh, you know, who needs American support of Israel? We
should be self-sufficient or whatever, right? So, you know, so how much
do you accept it, which is obviously doing a tremendous good? How
much you say no, excuse me, we want to take we don't
want you, you know, we want this to be our responsibility. So
it's a very interesting, what?
No, no, same thing, like money that goes right now to Israel.
Right, exactly. Government money that goes to...
Oh right, it's also right.
All the organizations...
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
The bitter irony is money goes to
numerous people who have this attitude and yet accept government money.
Exactly. Exactly.
Okay, so, alright. אמר ותניא אמר אבא בנימין הצדיק שהיה ממונה על
קופה של צדקה. amar v'tanya amar Abba Binyamin ha'tzaddik she'he'emun al kuppah
shel tzedakah. So בנימין הצדיק Binyamin HaTzaddik who was appointed over the...
He's an אמורא, Amora, בנימין הצדיק?
Binyamin HaTzaddik? Yeah, whatever, an אמורא, Amora, he lived in that time.
It's a תנא, sounds like it's a ברייתא. braita. Okay, פעם אחת
באה אשה לפניו בשני בצורת, pa’am achat ba’ah isha lifanav b’shnei batzoret,
a woman came to him in the time of famine. אמרה לו
רבי פרנסני Amrah lo Rebbi parneseini so you know sustain me. אמר
לה העבודה Amar lah ha-avodah
you know which is a way of saying like taking an oath
שאין בקופת של צדקה כלום She-ein be-kupat shel tzedakah klum I swear
to you it's empty, there's no money left. Obviously because it's a
time of famine and all the money's been given out.
אמרה לו רבי Amrah lo Rebbi אם אין אתה מפרנסני im ein
atah mifeneseini הרי אשה ושבעה בניה מתים harei ishah ve-shiva baneha metim
that you're signing me and my seven children to death. Again אשה
ושבעה בניה ishah ve-shiva baneha is a trope we you know that
exists otherwise. עמד ופרנסה משלו Amad u-farnesah mishelo so he supported her
out of his own money. Obviously a גבאי צדקה gabbai tzedakah does
not want to be doing that too often right because everybody's gonna
you know be asking you to stick your hand into your own
pocket.
Anyway לימים חלה ונטה למות le-yamim chalah ve-nata lamut then
there after a you know after a number of years he was
he was on his deathbed.
אמרו מלאכי השרת לפני הקדוש ברוך הוא Amru malachei ha-shareit lifnei ha-kadosh
baruch hu רבונו של עולם ribbono shel olam אתה אמרת כל המקיים
נפש אחת מישראל כאילו קיים עולם מלא atah amarta kol ha-mekayeim nefesh
achat mi-yisrael ke-ilu kiyem olam malei you said whoever supports one soul
is like they support an entire world.
ובנימין הצדיק שהחיה אשה ושבעה בניה u-binyamin ha-tzadik she-hechiyah ishah ve-shiva baneha
ימות בשנים מועטות yamut be-shanim mu-atot and this righteous person who supported
this woman he will die at such a young
age, again הללו בשנים מועטות? halalu be-shanim mu-atot? מיד קרעו לו גזר
דינו mi-yad kar'u lo gzar dino they tore up his decree.
Okay תניא it's a ברייתא braita הוסיפו לו עשרים ושתים שנה על
שנותיו hosifu lo esrim ve-shtayim shanah al shenotav they added 22 years
now of course I don't know who was up there in heaven
who overheard this but I imagine what happened was he was about
to die and he recovered and he lived for 22 more years.
And why was it 22?
I have no idea. תנו רבנן tanu rabbanan מעשה במונבז המלך ma-aseh
be-munbaz ha-melech מונבז המלך Munbaz the King who was from the
בית חשמונאי beit chashmonai okay שבזבז אוצרותיו ואוצרות אבותיו she-bizbez otzrotav ve-otzrot
avotav he basically you know squandered oh there's gotta be a better
word than squandered because squandered means wasted but he there is a
sense of that he completely distributed all of the money that he
had and that his you know family had the house of the
חשמונאים chashmonaim okay?
So ואוצרות אבותיו ve-otzrot avotav בשני בצורת bishnei batzoret in a time
of famine because everybody needed funds so he just emptied the you
know his coffers in order to support the poor and presumably also
all of his secret bank accounts in the you know in Switzerland
okay he took all of his private money and supported the poor
not just the government coffers. He was a son of הלני המלכה
Heleni ha-malkah okay בשנות בצורת bishnot batzoret in a time of famine.
וחברו עליו אחיו ובית אביו ve-chavru alav echav u-veit aviv so the
whole family started yelling at him you're throwing away all our money.
ואמרו לו ve-amru lo אבותיך גנזו והוסיפו
על של אבותם avotecha ganezu ve-hosifu al shel avotam your you know
your father anyway whatever you know every single generation has been adding
to our family fortune and you know ואתה מבזבז ve-atah mevazbez and
you're taking all of the money that we've stored up and you're
wasting it you're throwing it out? אמר להם אבותי גנזו למטה ואני
גנזתי למעלה avotai ganezu le-mata ve-ani ganazti le-ma-ala
they gathered for things down here I've gathered for up in heaven.
שנאמר she-ne-emar אמת מארץ תצמח וצדק משמים נשקף emet me-eretz titzmach ve-tzedek
mi-shamayim nishkaf
truth sort of sprouts from the ground and if you do צדקה
down here then you know the צדקה will come from up from
up heaven.
By the way מונבז Munbaz a proselyte maybe?
There's two comments here
one says that he was a Gentile king who converted oh interesting
if he
converted what's the אבות ואבות אבותיך? avot ve-avot avotecha?
אבותי avotai I guess he had another word your father what?
I guess yeah okay but the
other one רש"י Rashi says חשמונאי chashmonai think he was a son
of Queen Helena.
Aha question
right it's interesting okay so it's interesting if he was a convert
then it's very interesting this whole thing about his family right unless
it means his non-Jewish family oh then it would oh I see
then it has a very different tone then the point is here
he converted he became Jewish he understood the importance of צדקה and
then his all of his biological family is coming and telling him
telling him how stupid were you you wasted all our money okay
that's a very different tone that's very interesting okay. אבותי גנזו במקום
שהיד שולטת בו avotai ganezu be-makom she-ha-yad sholetet bo okay ואני גנזתי
במקום שאין היד שולטת
בו ve-ani ganazti be-makom she-ein ha-yad sholetet bo they put in a
place where a hand could reach it where it could get lost
you know get stolen or whatever I put in a place where
it's totally safe anybody who knows הלכות שבת hilchot shabbat also there's
יד שולטת בו yad sholetet bo different context. שנאמר she-ne-emar צדק ומשפט
מכון כסאך tzedek u-mishpat mechon kisecha you know right צדק tzedek again
like צדקה is in your you know is in the is the
foundation of your heavenly throne so it's up in heaven it's protected.
אבותי גנזו דבר שאינו עושה פירות avotai ganezu davar she-eino oseh peirot
they did something that you know there they didn't put it into
something that had a you know had a that that got interest
they you know they only saved the principal they didn't you know
they didn't invest it as it were. ואני גנזתי דבר שעושה פירות
ve-ani ganazti davar she-oseh peirot I invested it. How did I invest
it? שנאמר אמרו צדיק כי טוב כי פרי מעלליהם יאכלו imru tzadik
ki tov ki pri ma-alaleihem yocheilu so again צדיק and צדקה eat
the fruit of their actions so that's you know things that are
קרן קיימת לו לעולם הבא keren kayemet lo le-olam ha-ba אדם אוכל
פירותיהם בעולם הזה והקרן קיימת לו לעולם הבא adam ochel peiroteihem ba-olam
ha-zeh ve-ha-keren kayemet lo le-olam ha-ba you gain benefit in this world
from the merit and you still the principal is waiting for you.
אבותי גנזו אוצרות ממון ואני גנזתי אוצרות נפשות avotai ganezu otzrot mamon
ve-ani ganazti otzrot nefashot they just stored away money I stored away
souls. שנאמר פרי צדיק עץ חיים ולוקח נפשות חכם pri tzadik etz
chayim ve-lokeiach nefashot chacham so again the צדיק in צדקה and one
who takes souls so you save you know so you
save lives or or it's you know of religious
a religious value. ואני גנזתי לעצמי. v'ani ganzti l'atzmi. Now that's very
interesting. You would have expected the opposite. You're wasting it, you're giving
it to others, we should be saving it for ourselves. So he
turns it around. He says no, no, no, they wasted it because
what do you do? You save up all your money and then
you die!
I have it protected for myself. I found a way, you know,
what do they say? You can't take it with you? I found
a way to take it with me by giving it all away.
That's how I'm going to take it with me. שנאמר ולך תהיה
צדקה, Shene'emar u'lecha tihiyeh tzedakah, for you will remain צדקה even after
you die.
אבותיי גנזו לעולם הזה ואני גנזתי לעולם הבא. Avotai ganzu l'olam hazeh
v'ani ganzti l'olam haba. שנאמר והלך לפניך צדקך כבוד השם יאספך. Shene'emar
v'halach l'fanecha tzidkecha k'vod Hashem ya'asfecha. This will be standing for me
for the future times. Some of these sound like pretty parallel, but
nevertheless beautiful story. Okay, that is the end of that major סוגיא
of צדקה. Now, returning back to the last line of the משנה.
mishna. You might remember the משנה. mishna. We got onto this because
of the whole discussion of what the towns people can force, you
know, or can compel other members of the town to do, and
when you, you know, and how long you have to be in
the town to give to different parts of the charities and to
or to different types of contributions. So there was one opinion that
it's twelve months, but if you bought a house or an apartment
I guess, then it's immediately. ואם קנה בה בית דירה הרי הוא
כאנשי העיר. v'im kanah bah beit dirah harei hu k'anshei ha'ir. מתניתין
דלא כרבן שמעון בן גמליאל. matnitin d'lo k'Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel. דתניא,
d'tanya, it says in a ברייתא: braita: רבן שמעון בן גמליאל אומר
אם קנה בה קרקע כל שהוא הרי הוא כאנשי העיר. Rabban Shimon
ben Gamliel omer im kanah bah karka kol shehu harei hu k'anshei
ha'ir. You don't have to yet buy a house, you just have
to buy a little bit of land. By the way, you know,
that's the whole story about of course in חיי שרה, Chayei Sarah,
about why it was so hard for אברהם Avraham to buy the
plot, because once you buy a plot of land, I mean you
could say maybe דווקא davka a cemetery which shows real permanence because
it's going to be buried there forever, but the sense of owning
land in a place means that you're, you know, gives you a
sense of, you know, of a right to be there. Okay, so
he says even a little piece of land. והתניא, רבן שמעון בן
גמליאל אומר אם קנה שם קרקע הראויה לבית דירה הרי הוא כאנשי
העיר. Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel omer im kanah sham karka hara'uyah l'beit
dirah harei hu k'anshei ha'ir. It doesn't, it's not enough that it's
a plot of land. It has to be a plot of land
that would be fit for building a house. I guess so big
enough but also like if you maybe buy some acreage out in
the middle of nowhere for growing wheat, that might not count, right,
although that wouldn't be in the town though. But anyway it has
to be a place where we can see you building a house
and living here. תרי תנאי ואליבא דרבן שמעון בן גמליאל. trei tanna'ei
v'aliba d'Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel. Fine, it's a debate of רבן שמעון
בן גמליאל, Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel, but he doesn't need it to
be literally a house, even certain cases of land would suffice. Now,
next משנה. mishna. Back to this whole issue you might remember where
we were dealing about dividing a חצר, chatzer, building a wall, making
your neighbor build a wall, compelling the people in the town to
contribute to things for the sake of the town. So now we're
going to sort of shift within that discussion back to dividing things
up between like shared property. אין חולקין את החצר עד שיהא ארבע
אמות לזה וארבע אמות לזה. ein cholkin et hachatzer ad sheyehei arba
amot lazeh v'arba amot lazeh. You cannot force if you have a
shared yard with somebody else, you have two houses in a shared
yard, you cannot force them to divide the yard unless each one
can get ארבע אמות. arba amot. Now it doesn't tell me is
that ארבע אמות arba amot by ארבע אמות, arba amot, for you
know this is a little complicated because if you really think, try
to think about it because it's never exactly always clear what the
two dimensions are. But anyway, until each one gets ארבע אמות. arba
amot. Okay, ארבע אמות לזה וארבע אמות לזה. arba amot lazeh v'arba
amot lazeh. ולא את השדה עד שיהא בה תשעה קבין לזה ותשעה
קבין לזה. v'lo et hasadeh ad sheyehei bah tisha kavin lazeh v'tisha
kavin lazeh. And with a field for growing wheat there has to
be nine קבין, kavin, which is you know, it's a different measure.
It's like acres or whatever. Enough so that you could grow something
of significance. רבי יהודה אומר, Rabbi Yehuda omer, what?
Is קבין kavin square or is it still a length and...
No, that's sure קב kav I think is an area measurement. Right,
that's true. An אמה amah is a length measurement, but a קב
kav is an area measurement, so at least that's more understandable what
it's referring to. Okay, by the way, ארבע אמות arba amot is
not a lot. ארבע אמות arba amot is six feet, okay? So
if I have my house and I have a whole six feet
in front, like that's a tiny little space, okay? It's not like
we think of having a nice front yard, okay? But so it's
as, but as long as you get that minimum amount the other
person's entitled to force you to divide this field.
קב kav is that a measure of volume?
It's a measure of volume, but in a... applied, right, applied to
land it has to do with the amount of seed that fits
in a קב, kav, right, okay, yeah, all right.
So it translates into acreage. ולא את הגינה עד שיהא בה חצי
קב לזה וחצי קב לזה. v'lo et hagina ad sheyehei bah chatzi
kav lazeh v'chatzi kav lazeh. If it however is a garden for
like vegetables you don't need, you know, if that can be meaningful
even a lot smaller, not nine half קבין kavin but one half
קב. kav.
I'm sorry, I skipped a line. רבי יהודה אומר, Rabbi Yehuda omer,
back to the field, עד שיהא בה תשעה חצאי קבין לזה ותשעה
חצאי קבין לזה. ad sheyehei bah tisha chatzei kavin lazeh v'tisha chatzei
kavin lazeh. That for a field it's not nine קבין, kavin, it's
nine half קבין. kavin. ולא את הגינה עד שיהא בה חצי קב
לזה וחצי קב לזה. v'lo et hagina ad sheyehei bah chatzi kav
lazeh v'chatzi kav lazeh. And a garden is a lot smaller, okay,
even a half קב kav because vegetable garden you need less acreage.
רבי עקיבא אומר בית רובע. Rabbi Akiva omer beit rova. A quarter
of a קב. kav. Okay, even half of that. ולא את הטרקלין
ולא את המורן ולא את השובך. v'lo et hatraklin v'lo et hamoran
v'lo et hashovach. So טרקלין traklin and מורן moran are רש״י Rashi
says are two types of like large houses, mansions. ולא את השובך
v'lo et hashovach and a שובך shovach is like a pigeon coop.
ולא את הטלית. v'lo et hatallit. Dovecote. Dovecote,
excuse me, not pigeons, doves. Is there a difference between doves and
pigeons? I don't think so. I think doves and pigeons are really
the same. Anyway, moving on, dovecote, okay, what... anyway, moving on, but
we don't like saying that יונה yona that נח Noach sent the
pigeon, much better have him sent a dove. I think they, I
think they're basically the same animal. Anyway, moving on, ולא את השובך
ולא את הטלית. v'lo et hashovach v'lo et hatallit. Now, we're... moving
here from like real estate to other things. You don't divide a
טלית, tallis, like a cloak doesn't mean a טלית tallis like in
terms of like a religious item, a cloak. ולא את המרחץ Velo
es hamerchatz or bathhouse. It's bizarre that we go to like clothing
and then back to like, you know, real estate type of things
or bathhouse. ולא בית הבד Velo beis habad or a place of
pressing olives. ולא בית השלחין. Velo beis hashlachin. Now we're going back
to fields. בית השלחין Beis hashlachin is a field that gets irrigated,
an irrigation field. A what? שלחין. Shlachin.
שלחין, Shlachin, really? My oh my god, my entire yeshiva life we
mispronounced it. What did I say? השולחין? Hashulchin? I don't even remember
what I just said now. שלחין. Shlachin. Okay. בית השלחין. Beis hashlachin.
עד שיש
בהן כדי לזה וכדי לזה. Ad she-yesh bahen kidei lazeh u-kidei lazeh.
So here it's actually interesting. Now we're not going to give a
fixed quantitative amount. You have to assess case by case, you know,
how big is the טלית tallis to begin with? How big is
the בית הבד beis habad to begin with? How big but it
has to be something that it's determined that each one has a
reasonable sized, you know, thing left over. Now, let's say I can
divide up my castle or whatever, my mansion, but what does it
mean כדי לזה? kidei lazeh? Right, let's say we have ten brothers
living in a house and each one gets a room. Does that
mean well we each got, I mean, you could live in a
room, people have apartments, right, or small one bedroom apartments. So then
it clarifies, it says: זה הכלל כל שיחלק ושמו עליו חולקין. Zeh
haklal kol sheyeichalek ushemo alav cholkin. It means you have to be
left with what's considered a smaller version of the same thing. So
it's not enough to say, well we used to be sharing a
mansion and now each one of us has a room. No, no,
no. We can only force the other, you can always divide it
if you want to, but you can only force the other person
to divide if you could say, no, now you have a smaller
mansion. But if it's no longer called a mansion, then you can't,
then you can't do it. Okay. ואם לאו
אין חולקין. Ve-im lav ein cholkin. And if not, you cannot force
it.
אימתי? Eimasai? Now, when is this true that it's limited to this
requirement? בזמן שאין שניהם רוצים. Bizman she-ein sheneihem rotzim. If the, you
know, if they don't agree. So it's about forcing the other person.
אבל בזמן ששניהם רוצים, Aval bizman she-sheneihem rotzim, if they both agree,
אפילו פחות מכאן יחלקו, afilu pachus mikan yachaloku, then divide whatever you
want. וכתבי הקדש. Vekisvei hakodesh. And that's obvious. But the point is
the last one. וכתבי הקדש אף על פי ששניהם רוצים לא יחלקו.
Vekisvei hakodesh af al pi she-sheneihem rotzim lo yachaloku. But if you
have scrolls, which is not just limited to Torah scrolls, I've got
a book of ישעיהו. Yeshayahu. You know, it's a very long ספר.
sefer. Okay. And I really like the beginning of ישעיהו, Yeshayahu, and
you really like the end. And remember they used this not for
ritual purposes but for learning purposes, right? So let's just, let's just
cut it in half. I'll take the first, you know, thirty, forty
פרקים, perakim, you take the other half. Why not? Okay. So no,
you know, you don't do that. It's a בזיון bizayon to וכתבי
הקדש. kisvei hakodesh.
ישעיהו Yeshayahu is not what...
Okay, you know, whatever. You said that, I didn't say that. Anyway,
moving on. No, you have to keep it as one. What are
you talking about? This is the איסור issur to try to divide
it into two. Okay, anyway, moving on. But you know, it is
true, the whole sense, right? No, I'm serious about, you know, about,
about the, about the... like the sanctity of a book, you know,
that we have, I think, like we have this ethos as Jews,
like to me, like, you know, like the idea that you would
fold pages in a book, and I guess writing in the margins,
like writing in the גמרא, Gemara but like, but like imagine, let's
say, I don't know, let's like say imagine, you know, I had
a book and we wanted to sort of both read it at
the same time. Okay, well just cut it in half, you take
half and I'll take half. It's not an expense issue. I think
we have this like real sensibility to like, you know, a certain
sense of like, you know, of an attitude towards, towards the book.
I understand, these are scrolls, these are תנ״ך Tanakh scrolls, but I'm
just expanding the sort of sensibility here. Yes.
You can't put a book out on the floor.
It's immediately...
So yeah, but certainly here we're talking about תנ״ך Tanakh scrolls. Okay.
But again, but not for ritual purposes, for learning purposes. Let's take
a look at the גמרא. Gemara אמר רב אסי אמר רבי יוחנן:
Amar Rav Assi amar Rabbi Yochanan: ארבע אמות שאמרו חוץ של פתחים.
Arba amos she-amru chutz shel pesachim. Okay. One minute. First, everybody's got
to get a little space in front of their front door. And
then we talk about the getting four אמות amos in the yard.
Okay, so if you basically, right, have here's your yard, okay, here's
your house, okay, and here's the other house at the other end.
Okay, so what you do is, as is going to be clear
in the גמרא, Gemara or not so clear, but whatever, because this
problem only speaks in one dimension. You go four אמות amos opposite,
oh, here's the door of the house. Okay, here, I don't know,
let's make this the whole house. Okay, mansion. That's a mansion.
Exactly. It's not a very big field, right? It's a very long
flat house. Okay, anyway. Okay. You go four אמות amos in front,
okay, and he goes four אמות amos in front. And if after
that you get that space opposite the front door, six feet. It's
not a lot. Okay, I made it look like a lot. It's
really not a lot. Six, no, not by six feet. Six feet
by the width of the, by the width of the door. By
the width of the door.
So if a door is, it's not a lot, but it's like
a little, a little space that you can put stuff down, put
down your grocery bags, whatever. After each one gets... little space by
their front door, okay, then you look at the rest. And if
the rest has enough for ארבע אמות arba amot. *arba amot* per
person, and again, ארבע אמות amot. *arba amot* by what? I don't
know exactly. Does it mean ארבע אמות amot *arba amot*, does it
mean ארבע אמות amot *arba amot* by the width of the חצר
Chatzer? *chatzer*? You know, does it mean I don't know exactly, but
anyway if after that each one gets ארבע אמות amot *arba amot*,
then you can divide the rest. Okay. ארבע אמות amot שהן חוץ
מן הפתחים. תניא נמי הכי, Tanya Nami Hachi, אין חולקין את החצר
עד שיהא בה שמונה אמות amot. לזה ושמונה אמות amot, לזה. *Arba
amot shehen chutz min haptachim. Tanya nami hachi, ein cholkin et hachatzer
ad sheyehei bah shemoneh amot lazeh ushmoneh amot lazeh*. שמונה אמות amot.
*Shemoneh amot*? והאנן תנן ארבע אמות. amot. *Ve'anan tenan arba amot*. So
rather than saying they debate, we're going to say the following: ארבע
אמות amot. לזה וארבע אמות amot. לזה, אלא שמע מינה כדרב אסי
שמע מינה. *Arba amot lazeh ve'arba amot lazeh, ella shema mina kiderav
Assi shema mina*. It must mean ארבע אמות amot *arba amot* for
their פתחים *ptachim* and then an additional ארבע אמות amot. *arba amot*,
then that's the ארבע אמות amot. לזה וארבע אמות לזה *arba amot
lazeh ve'arba amot lazeh* is after the פתחים *ptachim*. But that all
works if we're doing directly opposite the פתחים *ptachim*. What about all
the side space, you know? So that's why it's a little confusing.
But then so you can say שמונה אמות *shemoneh amot* if you're
counting the whole length, then you could say ארבע אמות *arba amot*
if you first discount the space in front of the פתחים *ptachim*.
Okay. ואיכא דרמי ליה מירמי. *Ve'ika derami lei mirmey*. So some start
with a contradiction. תנן *Tenan*, our משנה *Mishnah*
says
אין חולקין את החצר שיש בה ארבע אמות לזה וארבע אמות לזה.
*ein cholkin
et hachatzer sheyesh bah arba amot lazeh ve'arba amot lazeh*. ארבע אמות
*Arba amot*. והתניא *Vehatanya*, we taught in the ברייתא baraita. *Barisa*, שמונה
אמות לזה ושמונה אמות לזה. *shemoneh amot lazeh ushmoneh amot lazeh*. אמר
רב אסי אמר רבי יוחנן ארבע אמות שהן חוץ מן הפתחים. *Amar
Rav Assi amar Rabbi Yochanan, arba amot shehen chutz min haptachim*. Fine.
You get four after you're done with the space in front of
the doors. אמר רב הונא חצר מתחלקת לפי פתחיה. *Amar Rav Huna,
chatzer mitchaleket lefi ptacheiha*.
It's divided according to the doors. Okay, now, which is wild, which
means that if I've got a house and it's got two doors,
right, okay, and you've got one that's got one door, okay, I
get two-thirds of the חצר *chatzer*, forget the amount in front of
the houses, I get two-thirds of the חצר *chatzer* and you get
one-third. So it's like, you know, so before anybody splits up a
חצר *chatzer* you should start building a lot of doors into your
house. Big family house? I understand, maybe, but it didn't say that.
Maybe you're right, maybe a classic reason you'd have multiple doors is
if there's a different family. But then you could say לפי דיורין
*lefi diyurin*, not לפי פתחים *lefi ptachim*. Anyway, so that's what רב
אסי *Rav Assi* says. אמר רב הונא חצר לפי פתחיה. *Amar Rav
Huna, chatzer lefi ptacheiha*. ורב חסדא אמר *VeRav Chisda amar*, no, נותנין
ארבע אמות לכל פתח ופתח והשאר חולקין בשוה. *notin arba amot lechol
petach upetach vehash'ar cholkin beshava*. Every door gets its own ארבע אמות
*arba amot* in front of the door, but then the rest is
divided equally. That makes a lot of sense. Okay. ותניא כוותיה דרב
חסדא *Vetanya kevatei deRav Chisda*, we taught like רב חסדא *Rav Chisda*.
פתחים שבחצר יש להם ארבע אמות. *Ptachim shebachatzer yesh lahem arba amot*.
Each doorway has ארבע אמות *arba amot* in front of it. היה
לזה פתח אחד ולזה שני פתחים, זה שיש לו פתח אחד נוטל
ארבע אמות, וזה שיש לו שני פתחים נוטל שמונה אמות, והשאר חולקין
בשוה. *Haya lazeh petach echad u'lazeh shenei ptachim, zeh sheyesh lo petach
echad notel arba amot, vezeh sheyesh lo shenei ptachim notel shemoneh amot,
vehash'ar cholkin beshava*. Okay, you get ארבע אמות *arba amot* per door
and then the rest is divided equally. היה לזה פתח רחב שמונה
אמות, נוטל שמונה אמות כנגד הפתח וארבע אמות בחצר.
*Haya lazeh petach rachav shemoneh amot,
notel shemoneh amot keneged hapetach ve'arba amot bachatzer*. Now here's where the,
how did they add those two ארבע אמות *arba amot* together? Right,
especially if it's like directly in front, because then they don't combine.
Right, but that, but the reason to say directly by the width
of the door, until now you could have gotten away without saying
that, but it's this next line. Okay. היה לזה פתח רחב שמונה
אמות, נוטל שמונה אמות כנגד הפתח וארבע אמות בחצר. *Haya lazeh petach
rachav shemoneh amot, notel shemoneh amot keneged hapetach ve'arba amot bachatzer*. If
your פתח *petach* was שמונה אמות *shemoneh amot* wide, you get שמונה
אמות *shemoneh amot* opposite the פתח *petach*. Now what does it mean?
שמונה אמות *Shemoneh amot* length? וארבע אמות בחצר *ve'arba amot bachatzer*, and
four amot in the חצר *chatzer*. So how do you parse that?
So גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says, ארבע אמות בחצר מאי עבידתיה? *arba amot
bachatzer mai avidtei*? What do you mean? You're talking about the door
and then you talk about the חצר *chatzer*? אמר אביי הכי קאמר:
*Amar Abaye hachi ka'amar*: נוטל שמונה אמות באורך החצר וארבע אמות ברוחב
החצר. *notel shemoneh amot be'orech hachatzer ve'arba amot berovach hachatzer*,
which basically means ארבע אמות *arba amot* into, you know, in front
of the door, and the width of the part of the yard
you get is the width of the door. So if the width
of the door is שמונה אמות *shemoneh amot*, you get a full
שמונה אמות *shemoneh amot*. I assume the width of the door is
less than four, it's probably the minimum is probably four by four.
Okay, but here you see that you get ארבע אמות *arba amot*
into it by the width of the door. That's assumed by a
minimum of four, but expand up to the width of the door,
you know, going as wide as the door.
Yeah, ארבע אמות *arba amot* is
a very wide door.
That's a huge door.
Right, I'm not saying a standard door, I'm not saying a standard
door is, oh, you mean שמונה אמות *shemoneh amot* is huge? שמונה
אמות *Shemoneh amot* is totally huge. Yes. Okay, so now the גמרא
*Gemara* says like this. אמר אביי *Amar Abaye*, right, it's like what,
is it twelve feet? אמר אביי הכי קאמר *Amar Abaye hachi ka'amar*,
I
already got through that. Okay. אמר אמימר האי פירא דסופלי *Amar Ameimar,
hai pira desufli*, if you have a, רש"י Rashi *Rashi* says it's
like a type of a ditch where you put into it dates,
seeds, what does רש"י Rashi *Rashi* say? Yeah, date
seeds. יש לו ארבע אמות לכל רוח ורוח. *Yesh lo arba amot
lechol ruach varuach*. So in my yard, like I've got a little,
you know, thing that I plant date seeds, so that gives me
ארבע אמות *arba amot* I get around each side because I've got
to get access to that. Okay, so it's very interesting. Again, like
the more you're going to divide up the yard, the more you
want to have more things going on in the yard because it
gives you then rights to keep, to hold on to them. Okay.
ולא אמרן אלא דלא מייחד ליה פיתחא. *Velo amaran ela delo meyached
leh pitzcha*. That's only if you don't have a door that directly
opens into it. אבל מיחד ליה פתחא אין לו אלא ארבע אמות
לפני פתחא, then you only have four אמות. So the way it
sounds like is, you know, like the way רש"י, Rashi if I
understand רש"י Rashi correctly, is if I've got my house here, okay?
And I've got in my backyard, whatever this thing is, this ditch,
okay? Then I need four אמות around it to get me access
to the ditch. To the ditch? Yeah. But if I've got, but
if I've got a back door opening into it, then I only
need the space directly in front of the back door because that'll
get me immediate access. Although I really must say I really don't
understand this, because if I only have a front door and I
have to go around, that doesn't explain why I have four אמות
on each side. Four אמות on each side is not necessarily going
to give me access.
This is so connected to how Babylonian,
I'm sure, designed their home.
Right. We got to do the best we can.
יעקב אלמן's Yaakov Elman like...
I don't know, I don't know. But anyway, I think it's best
that we be honest that we don't fully understand it. At least
I don't fully understand it. Okay. אמר רבא אמר רב הונא. Amar
Rava Amar Rav Huna. Okay. Now it gets maybe a little more
manageable. אכסדרה אין לה ארבע אמות. Achsadra ein la arba amot. An
אכסדרה, achsadra, which is a portico, which is basically, I mean, there's
a debate, תוספות Tosafot claims that it has three walls, but פשוט
pashut is it doesn't. Right? You've got, you know, you've seen these
things, these like whatever, right? Is that what it's called? A portico?
Okay. Yes, no, is that what that's called?
You can't see what I'm drawing. This is a roof. You really
don't see? It's a beautiful drawing. Okay, anyway. This is the roof.
These are pillars holding it up. A basilica? Is that what it's
called? Not a basilica. No, they had this in Roman time.
Are there walls at all on...
Oh, a pavilion? Okay. Anyway, you walk around underneath it. What? No
walls. No walls. Open air.
Two different opinions.
I know, I know. תוספות Tosafot says, I know, תוספות Tosafot says
that there were three walls. But we're going to read it רש"י's
Rashi way.
It's like a world's fair pavilion.
All right, can we please move on? Okay. אכסדרה אין לה ארבע
אמות. Achsadra ein la arba amot. טעמא מאי משום פירוק משאו. Taama
mai mishum peruk masao. Listen, now finally we understand why are you
given four אמות in front of your door. Okay, because you have
to unload your donkey. You got all your groceries, you got to
put them down, you got to get your keys, you got to
open it up, so you need a little space. Okay. So the
גמרא says here, you don't have to unload things in front of
the door. You just walk straight in. Okay. טעמא מאי משום פירוק
משאו. Taama mai mishum peruk masao. הכא אפשר דעייל לגואי ומפרק. Hacha
efshar de-ayeil legavai u-mfarek. Just go straight in and then you unload
it on, you know, you know in that space. So again we're
talking about the אכסדרה. achsadra. So again תוספות Tosafot says maybe there's
only one open wall. You don't need all four open walls in
order to save it. מתיבי רב ששת. Matvei Rav Sheshet. רב ששת
Rav Sheshet asks on this. We have a ברייתא. baraita אחד שערי
בתים ואחד שערי אכסדראות יש להן ארבע אמות. Echad shaarei batim ve-echad
shaarei achsadraot yesh lahen arba amot. We said that whether you're dealing
with the gate of a house or even the gate walking into
this אכסדרה, achsadra, this portico, whatever it is, that you have four
אמות. And you're saying you don't? כי תניא ההיא באכסדרה דבי רב.
Ki tanya hahi be-achsadra de-vei Rav. Now that's about the type of
something called the אכסדרה achsadra of the students or whatever, דבי רב,
de-vei Rav, which רש"י Rashi says basically means, what does רש"י Rashi
say it means? Oh, that it did have walls around it. Okay.
You couldn't just walk straight in. Or it had partial walls. So
the גמרא says אכסדרה דבי רב כעיטי דעיטי achsadra de-vei Rav ke-iti
de-iti obviously, אדרונא מעליא היא, Idrona malya hi, that's a real room.
That's a real... אדרונא idrona is the Aramaic word for חדר. cheder.
אלא באכסדרה רומיתא. Ela be-achsadra Rumita. Fine. A Roman אכסדרה achsadra which
is... or which רש"י Rashi says has like very low walls, okay?
But so even though it's not as obvious because it has low
walls, you might think that you don't get the four אמות, but
you do get the four אמות. All right, keep moving on. תנו
רבנן. Tano Rabbanan. בית שער אכסדרה ומרפסת יש להן ארבע אמות. Beit
shaar achsadra u-mirpeset yesh lahen arba amot.
So this is the ברייתא Braita that said that an אכסדרה achsadra
does get four אמות. So if you have a
gate house, or an אכסדרה, achsadra, or a even a מרפסת. mirpeset.
Now, a מרפסת mirpeset here means, as we're gonna see...
you've got, you know, you know in those like motels when you...
I think this is the best way to describe it, you know,
every... you know, you go up to the second story and on
the outside and there's like a shared, you know,
walkway. That's the מרפסת. mirpeset. That basically you have multiple people who
are sharing an upper עליה, aliya, okay? You know, it's a multi-family
thing. Okay, they're like second story. Okay, and there's the house here,
and there's this מרפסת. mirpeset. Right, that everybody shares. Okay. And the
מרפסת mirpeset there's stairs that go down into the courtyard. Here's the
courtyard. Okay. So, the opening here has four אמות. Okay. So that...
that's it. Isn't that a gorgeous drawing? Because מיכל Michal didn't like
my other drawing. Okay, fine. Okay. בית שער אכסדרה ומרפסת יש להן
ארבע אמות. Beit shaar achsadra u-mirpeset yesh lahen arba amot. היו חמשה
בתים פתוחין למרפסת. Hayu chamisha batim petuchin la-mirpeset. This is what I
just described, five separate homes open onto the מרפסת mirpeset here. אין
להן אלא ארבע אמות בלבד. Ein lahen ela arba amot bilvad. No,
you only get four אמות. Like where רש"י says where the steps
descend into the courtyard. בעי מיניה רבי יוחנן מרבי ינאי. Ba-i minei
Rabbi Yochanan me-Rabbi Yannai. רבי יוחנן asks רבי ינאי. Rabbi Yannai. לול
של תרנגולין יש לו ארבע אמות או אין לו ארבע אמות? Lul
shel tarnigolin yesh lo arba amot o ein lo arba amot? I
have a chicken coop in the courtyard. Okay, so do I get
the four אמות in front of the chicken coop? So the chickens
don't need the four אמות. גמרא says: אמר ליה, Amar leh, טעמא
מאי? Ta'ama mai? משום פירוק משאו. Mishum perik mas'oh. Why do we
give you? In order to like unload your burden. So you're not
actually walking with your burden into the chicken coop. הכא מטפי שלוש
ומטפי יורא, Hacha mitapi shelosh mitapi yorei, so roughly so the chickens
can hop their way in and hop their way out, they don't
need the four אמות. Okay,
בעי מיניה רבא מרב נחמן. Ba'ei minei Rava me'Rav Nachman. בית חציו
מקורה וחציו אינו מקורה, Ba'is chatzyo mekurah ve'chatzyo eino mekurah, יש ארבע
אמות או אין לו ארבע אמות? yesh arba amot o ein lo
arba amot? So let's say half of it has a ceiling and
half of it doesn't have a ceiling, okay? So the point being
that if the half that doesn't have a ceiling, if it's the
outer half, if it's the half facing the front door, then apparently
I can walk in without unloading my burdens because I gave the
example, I was trying to contemporize it, and I said you have
to put down your groceries and get your keys. But that's really
not the issue. The issue is you've got your burden on your
donkey, and you can't walk in that takes, that's too like whatever,
a height problem is what רש"י makes it sound, with walking in
with your donkey, otherwise you'd be happy to walk in with your
donkey into your house. But because of like the burdens and you
know, maybe, maybe it's not just as wide, you got this big,
you know, whatever, big bundle of straw on top of the donkey.
Exactly, so if it doesn't have a roof on top, then you
can walk in and you don't have to worry about that, you
walk in with your donkey and you unload it in your house.
So he says therefore you don't have to worry. Okay, מ- m-
so he says, אינו- יש לו ארבע אמות או אין לו, eino-
yesh lo arba amot o ein lo, אמר ליה, amar lei, אין
לו ארבע אמות, ein lo arba amot, you don't get ארבע אמות.
לא מיבעיא קירובו מלגיו, Lo miba'i keruva miligav, goes without saying if
the roofed part is on the inner side and the unroofed part
is towards the door, דאפשר דעייל לגואי ומפרק, de'efshar de'ayeil ligavai mefareik,
you can go inside and unload it in the first half of
the house, אלא אפילו קירובו כלפי חוץ, ela afilu keruva kelapei chutz,
even if the roofed part is on the outside and the unroofed
part is on the inside, דאפשר דעייל לגואי ומפרק, efshar de'ayeil ligavai
mefareik, you can still go through the roofed part and apparently what
you need the most height is when you're doing the act of
unloading, not just to walk through, and then you can unload it
there. You know, it's like in the front of every house they
would have a sign, clearance, twelve feet, you know, trucks exit here,
whatever. Okay, מ- m- okay. בעי מיניה רב הונא מרבי אמי. Ba'ei
minei Rav Huna me'Rabbi Ami. אחד מבני מבוי שביקש להחזיר פתחו למבוי
אחר, Echad mi'benei mavoy she'bikeish lehachazir pitcho lemavoy acher, בני מבוי מעכבינה
ליה או אין מעכבינה ליה? benei mavoy me'akveina lei o ein me'akveina
lei? Okay,
so basically
here what we're dealing now, it's not exactly the courtyard, it's a
מבוי. mavoy. Okay, the basic way it works was here you have
your individual homes opening into these חצירות, chatzeirot, okay? You have these
חצירות, chatzeirot, okay? These shared yards, and all the yards open up
into a מבוי, mavoy, into basically an alleyway or sometimes a רשות
הרבים. reshut harabim. Now let's say, you know, you basically had like
two מבויס, mavoys, okay? And this had other homes and other חצירות,
chatzeirot, okay? So you decided you're gonna create a door this way
and give yourself access, why just take access and go the long
way and go into that street? Just make a back door here
and get yourself direct access into that street, okay? So you're a
בני מבוי זה benei mavoy zeh and you're opening up your door
to give you access to another מבוי. mavoy. All right, is that
clear? All right, so... אחד מי- Echad mi-
what? Not clear?
No, it was good, but
I
don't think it's a bit, it's a bit. מבוי. Mavoy.
מבוי, Mavoy, thank you. Like מבוי סתום. mavoy satum. Okay, I am
so glad you are here, for once I am going to speak
proper, proper Hebrew. Okay, you have to understand, I grew up in,
I did not grow up in Israel, I grew up in ישיבות,
yeshivas, okay? So okay. Okay, thank you. No, thank you. אחד מבני
מבוי ש- she- שביקש להחזיר פתחו למבוי אחר, Echad mi'benei mavoy she'bikeish
lehachazir pitcho lemavoy acher, I'll tell you a joke at the end.
שביקש להחזיר פתחו למבוי אחר, She'bikeish lehachazir pitcho lemavoy acher, בני מבוי
מעכבינה ליה או אין מעכבינה ליה? benei mavoy me'akveina lei o ein
me'akveina lei? Can the people here say, no way buddy, you don't
have right to get access into our alleyway? אמר ליה, Amar lei,
בני מבוי מעכבינה ליה. benei mavoy me'akveina lei. Yeah, they can tell
him, sorry, that's our alleyway, not your alleyway. Now, אכסניא לפני בני
אדם
מתחלקת או לפני פתחים מתחלקת. achsanya lifnei benei adam mitchaleket o lifnei
petachim mitchaleket. Now what's an אכסניא? achsanya? We often talk about it
as an inn, but רש"י actually also says,
or תוס- Tos- yeah, רש"י says that basically it is, you know,
troops that are being housed, you know, you know,
in a certain in a building like a, and now they're dividing
up, presumably they open up into a, they share a courtyard. So
do you divide it based on the doorways? Do they get the
space in the courtyard based on the doorways or space in the
courtyard based on the number of people that are there?
תוספות Tosafot says it's a very different issue, it's a question as
what the גמרא'ס Gemara's immediately going to turn to is a question
where there's like shared זבל, zevel, you know, like garbage but it
turns into also fertilizer in the courtyard that came from the houses,
and that also gets divided based on the houses. So תוספות Tosafot
says that's the question. Everybody is sort of throwing their stuff into
a dump and you throw it out of your door. Do you
divide the זבל zevel based on the doors or based on the
people in the house?
Now basically here the soldiers are going to... into private homes being
forced by the government?
Not so clear. Not so clear. Where it actually says he says
it to be house, I don't know about forced, like it might
be the town's responsibility to quarter troops. That's right.
Yeah, it's quartering, it's quartering troops.
It's one of the, right, rights of the, right, what's one of
the, right, what do you, yeah, so okay, here was before the
Bill of Rights, they had a quarter troops. אמר ליה לפי בני
אדם מתחלקת Amar Lei L'fi Bnei Adam Mit-chaleket
based on the number of people, not based on the number of
doorways, whether you're talking about dividing the courtyard or dividing the fertilizer.
תניא נמי הכי, we taught similarly, זבל שבחצר Zebel She-be-chatzer because that's
why תוספות Tosafot were saying that earlier, מתחלקת
לפי פתחים. Mit-chaleket L'fi P'tachim. Apparently, so when you're coming to divide
the amount of fertilizer that got collected through everybody's garbage and animals
and dung. אכסניא לפי בני אדם, Ach-sanya L'fi Bnei Adam,
but if it's this quartering of troops, then it goes by the
people, not by the doors. I guess because that's just a more
meaningful way of dividing it in that context. אמר רב הודה, Amar
Rav Huda, אחד מבני מבוי שביקש לסתום כנגד פתחו, Echad Mi-bnei Mavoy
She-bikesh Lis-tom K'neged Pitcho, בני מבוי מעכבין עליו, Bnei Mavoy Me-akvin Alav,
שהרבה עליהם את הדרך. She-hir-bah Alei-hem Et Ha-derech.
So here, we're talking about one מבוי, Mavoy,
okay, and you have all of these חצירות Chatzeirot that are open,
okay. Now, I am going to read this רש"י's way because just,
I mean תוספות's Tosafot way, because just it's easier. Okay, which is,
I've got, we all have shared rights, this is more, better thought
of as an alleyway rather than as a street, okay, because it's
private. We all have shared rights to this private alleyway. But basically,
I'm back here and I'm saying, look guys, basically we all need
to go out here to get to the רשות הרבים. Reshut Ha-rabim.
Okay, there's a רשות הרבים Reshut Ha-rabim here. Okay, but nobody really
needs to go way back here. No? So as long as this
is sort of, my house is here, and why do you, what
do you guys need? I'm just going to use that all for
my private space. I'm going to put a wall here and just
make that my own little private space, okay. What does it bother
you? Okay, so that's what I want to do,
okay. So אחד מבני מבוי, Echad Mi-bnei Mavoy, where were we, שביקש
לסתום כנגד פתחו, She-bikesh Lis-tom K'neged Pitcho, I'm just going to, right
there, I'm just going to take that for myself. בני מבוי מעכבין
עליו. Bnei Mavoy Me-akvin Alav. No, somebody, they can tell him no
buddy, you can't do that. שהרבה עליהם את הדרך. She-hir-bah Alei-hem Et
Ha-derech. Now שהרבה עליהם את הדרך She-hir-bah Alei-hem Et Ha-derech might sound
like you have to go out of your way. So רש"י reads
it in a way that reads it according to that. תוספות Tosafot
says שהרבה עליהם את הדרך She-hir-bah Alei-hem Et Ha-derech means you're going
to increase our foot traffic. Yes. Because if people can't use this
back space, they're going to be more people in the other space.
Exactly. So you'll increase our foot traffic. מיתיבי, Meitivei, they ask you,
חמש חצירות פתוחות למבוי, Chamesh Chatzeirot P'tuchot L'mavoy,
כולן משתמשין עם החיצונה. Kulan Mish-tam-shin Im Ha-chitzonah. Now here it's going
to say one minute, because we're going to have a ברייתא that
says that your rights to the מבוי, Mavoy, to parts of the
מבוי, Mavoy, are based on your need to get out of the,
out to the רשות הרבים. Reshut Ha-rabim. So if you have these
five places, okay, let's just make it like this, okay, we won't
do it in both directions, okay. So it says like this,
it says,
כולן משתמשין עם החיצונה. Kulan Mish-tam-shin Im Ha-chitzonah. Everybody can use the
space in front of the outer one because they all have to
go through the outer
one. והחיצונה משתמשת לעצמה, Ve-ha-chitzonah Mish-tameshet L'atzmah, but the outer one can
only use its space, it can't use any of the space behind
it. והשאר משתמשין עם השנייה. Ve-ha-sha'ar Mish-tam-shin Im Ha-shniya. Now all of
these can use the second one, but והשנייה, Ve-ha-shniya, the second one's
area in front of him, היא משתמשת לעצמה, Hi Mish-tameshet L'atzmah, but
the second one only has the space in front of him, ומשתמשת
עם החיצונה, U-mish-tameshet Im Ha-chitzonah, and the outer one, because you only
have from your courtyard to the way to get out.
Okay. נמצאת פנימית משתמשת לעצמה ומשתמשת עם כל אחת ואחת. Nim-tzeit P'nimit
Mish-tameshet L'atzmah U-mish-tameshet Im Kol Achat Ve-achat. The back one is the
one that has rights to the entire length of the מבוי, Mavoy,
its space and all of that, because it has to, because so,
because it has to get out through the length of all of
them. Which means that actually, this is yours, the part directly opposite
you is yours and these guys don't have a right to it,
so why not just seal off that space? Okay. So the גמרא
says תנאי היא, Tannai Hi, it's a debate of תנאים. Tannaim. דתניא,
De-tanya, אחד מבני מבוי שביקש להחזיר פתחו למבוי אחר, Echad Mi-bnei Mavoy
She-bikesh Le-hach-zir Pitcho L'mavoy Acher, בני מבוי מעכבין עליו. Bnei Mavoy Me-akvin
Alav. Okay,
so this first starts with other points. If you want to open
it to another מבוי, Mavoy, the other מבוי Mavoy can prevent you.
היה סתום וביקש לפותחו, Hayah Satum U-bikesh Le-pot-cho, if it was a
door that had been sealed, but originally it was open, and now
you want to reopen it. So that's a more interesting question. אין
בני מבוי מעכבין עליו, Ein Bnei Mavoy Me-akvin Alav, דברי רבי. Divrei
Rabbi. Rabbi says, okay, since you originally had the right, we can't
prevent you now to reopen. ורבי שמעון בן אלעזר אומר, Ve-Rabbi Shimon
Ben Elazar Omer, חמש חצירות הפתוחות למבוי כולן משתמשות במבוי זו עם
זו. Chamesh Chatzeirot Ha-p'tuchot L'mavoy Kulan Mish-tam-shot Ba-mavoy Zo Im Zo.
Okay,
and now he says they can all use each other's space. It's
not this idea you can only use your space and then going
out. So first of all, the גמרא says חצירות מאן דכר שמייהו,
Chatzeirot Man Dakar Sh-meihu, who's talking about a חצר? We were talking
about opening a door that had been sealed. So חסורי מחסרא והכי
קתני. Chisurei Michsera Ve-hachi Katani. So this is just fixing the text
of the... וכן חמש חצירות הפתוחות למבוי כולן משתמשת עם החיצונה והחיצונה
משתמשת לעצמה וכולי, Ve-chen Chamesh Chatzeirot Ha-p'tuchot L'mavoy Kulan Mish-tameshet Im Ha-chitzonah
Ve-ha-chitzonah Mish-tameshet L'atzmah Ve-chulu, דברי רבי. Divrei Rabbi. Okay,
so he said that part was missing. Rabbi says this idea that
you only have your space and going out, so which means the
guy in the back has that space uniquely to him and he
could wall it up. ורבי שמעון בן אלעזר אומר, Ve-Rabbi Shimon Ben
Elazar Omer, לא, חמש חצירות הפתוחות למבוי כולן משתמשות במבוי, Chamesh Chatzeirot
Ha-p'tuchot L'mavoy Kulan Mish-tam-shot Ba-mavoy, they all have equal rights and you
can't. wall it off. So before we end, first of all, יישר
כוח shkoach that we caught up and we have two minutes left,
so I just want to read you one last line in תוספות,
Tosafot, which is very interesting about the issue about zoning. So if
you look at תוספות, Tosafot, he says right before the end of
אחד, right before the תוספות הפנימית, Tosafot haPnimis, four lines up, it
says ובתוספתא דפרק קמא דמכילתין תניא U'vitossefta d'perek kama d'machiltin tanya יש
לו חנות ברשות הרבים yeish lo chanut birshut harabim ומבקש לפתחה לחצר.
u'mevakesh liftecha l'chatzer.
So you have your door, your store, and it's open to רשות
הרבים reshut harabim and you want the back of your door of
your store opens into a yard. So you want to open the
back into the yard, get a little bit more traffic, right? לחצר
השותפים, l'chatzer hashitufim, השותפין יכולים לעכב על ידו hashitufin yecholim l'akeiv al
yado מפני mipnei
שמרבה עליהם את הדרך. she'marbe aleihem et haderech. And תוספות Tosafot says
this means foot traffic. That's the way תוספות Tosafot reads הדרך. haderech.
So you cannot open your store in my courtyard because you're going
to increase the foot traffic in my courtyard. Okay, so it's a
real like zoning issue. You can't go ahead and do something that's
going to increase. Yes, Dave?
You don't necessarily need to say that the person who says that
the